M.C. LAWTON CIVIC AND CULTURAL CLUB RECORDS (APAP027) 1921-2004
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club Records 1921-2004
nam_apap027
M.C. Lawton Civic And Cultural Club
1.13
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
The M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club Records showcase the operations of the first black organization in Albany that was actively involved in community service and educational advancement, which was founded in 1919.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club, Inc. on April 17, 1990. An additional accession was received from Carol Praylor, President, in September 2004.
Organizational Sketch
The M.C. Lawton Club has its beginnings in the Women's Auxiliary of the 15th Infantry, a black unit active during World War I. At the end of the war, the members of the auxiliary decided to continue to associate as they had for the previous four years. In April 1919, the club was founded as the Marie C. Lawton Club in Albany, N.Y., as a branch of the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs. The club's goals were to "promote the welfare of people wherein needed, and to assist in civic affairs."[1] The club was the first black organization in Albany actively involved in "community service, educational advancement, race relations and self-development."[2] An important activity of the club was its annual concert showcasing promising young black musicians. The Club regularly sponsored dances to support causes such as scholarships for college students and Haiti. In 1926/1927, the Club was involved in advocacy on a number of important issues including performances by minstrels in the Albany Public Schools and housing conditions in the city. Out of this work the Club developed a five-point plan whcih was eventually taken over by the Albany Inter-Racial Council. By 1955, the club had consistently begun to use the name M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club.
The M.C. Lawton Club has close ties to other civic and cultural clubs in the Capital District, including the Albany Inter-Racial Council and the Community Chest. The club is affiliated with the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs, Inc.; the Northeastern Association of Women's Clubs; and the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs, Inc.
[1] M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club, Inc. Constitution, 1955.
[2] M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club, Inc. Musical Program, 1978.
Scope and Content Information
The minutes (1927-65, 1971-75) of the M.C. Lawton Club are its most substantial records. The earliest minutes (1919-26) are missing, but the minutes that remain give a good picture of the activities of the organization and how well it met those goals. Only scattered minutes for 2002-2004 are available in this collection. The remainder of the Club's minutes remain in with its members. Especially interesting are the earlier minutes when the club fought for racial justice at the local level in the fields of housing, education, and employment, presenting black speakers such as Countee Cullen to the population as a whole and decrying minstrel shows.
The correspondence (1921-23, 1928-31, 1943, 1950, 1953-59, 1973, 1977-78) primarily concerns routine administrative matters. Although the correspondence covers a wide range of years, most of the correspondence dates from the 1920's, 1950's, and 1970's, and consists mainly of thank you notes or other routine correspondence.
The reports (1928, 1930, 1932, 1935, 1949, 1973, 1975) are not extensive, but these are full of information about the club's activities. The musical programs (1936, 1955, 1957, circa 1964, 1968, 1971, 1975-80, 1985-87) contain little additional information other than the programs, which do include brief historical sketches of the club.
For related records, see the records of the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs, Inc. A photograph from the collection is available for viewing online from the University at Albany Libraries' Digital Collections database.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Minutes, 1927-2004, .80 cubic ft.
Series 2: Subject Files, 1921-2004, .33 cubic ft.
Series 1 is arranged chronologically while Series 2, is arranged alphabetically.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Albany, New York; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations
Subject and Genre Headings
M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club; National Association of Colored Women's Clubs (U.S.); Women--Societies and clubs; Women in nonprofit organizations; Albany (N.Y.); Clippings(information artifacts); Correspondence; Membership; Minutes; Programs (documents); Photographs
Container List
- Minutes, 1927-2004; 1; 0.80
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Minutes, ca. 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Papers removed from 1927-1930 minute book (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Papers removed from 1930-1932 minute book (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Papers removed from 1932-1936 minute book (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1941-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Papers removed from 1951-1957 minute book (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes and Agenda, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 1921-2004; 2; 0.33
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Albany Inter-Racial Council, 1929; 1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arbor Hill Community Dinner, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Awards Banquet Hosted by M.C. Lawton Club, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Awards to the M.C. Lawton Club, 1973; 1975; 1979; 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Child Health Meeting Notice, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Community Chest of Albany and Rensselaer, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Constitution, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Constitution and Handbook, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1923; 1928-1931 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1943; 1950; 1953-1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1973; 1977-1978; 2002-2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dinner Programs, 1954-1956; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs, Inc., Events Hosted by M.C. Lawton Club, Programs and Financial Report, 1994; 1998; 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - March on Washington Movement, Brochure, 1914-1915 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Membership, Correspondence and List, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mother and Daughter Banquest, Program, ca. 1958 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Musical Programs, 1936; 1955-1957; ca. 1964; 1968-1971; 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Musical Programs, 1980; 1985-1987; 1993; 2003 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - News Clippings, 1939; 1952; 1969; 1973-1980; 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings, 1939; 1952; 1969-1980; 1988-1989; 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - President, Carol Praylor, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Presidents and Vice Presidents, List, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Reports, Annual and Historian's, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Reports on Annual Conventions of the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs, 1949; 1973; 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Reports to Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs, 1928; 1930; 1932; 1935 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Scholarship Recipients, List, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 35th Anniversary Celebration, Invitation, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - 75th Anniversary Celebration, Program and Roster, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - 85th Anniversary Celebration, Program, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 30)